<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd at St. Clement-Danes, the 29th of Septemb. 1700 occasion'd by the recantation of Mr. Clement Joynes, (lately a Quaker) / by J. Adams ...</title>
            <author>Adams, John, 1662-1720.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26339</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A487</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21388</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12296886</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12296886</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59049</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26339)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59049)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 908:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd at St. Clement-Danes, the 29th of Septemb. 1700 occasion'd by the recantation of Mr. Clement Joynes, (lately a Quaker) / by J. Adams ...</title>
                  <author>Adams, John, 1662-1720.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for D. Brown ... and Peter Buck ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes the text of the recantation.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Joynes, Clement.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LXVI, 16 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59049:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59049:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd at St. <hi>Clement-Danes,</hi> the 29th of <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1700. Occaſion'd by the Recantation of Mr. <hi>Clement Joynes,</hi> (lately a <hi>Quaker.</hi>) By <hi>J. ADAMS.</hi> Chaplain in Ordinary to His MAJESTY. Publiſhed at the Requeſt of the Perſons concerned, and ſeveral others of that Pariſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>D. Brown</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar;</hi> and <hi>Peter Buck</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recantation">
            <pb facs="tcp:59049:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59049:2"/>
            <head>THE RECANTATION OF Mr. <hi>CLEMENT JOYNES.</hi> Read in the Pariſh Church of St. <hi>Clement Danes,</hi> the 29th of <hi>Sept.</hi> 1700.</head>
            <head type="sub">Publiſhed by his Deſire.</head>
            <p>I, <hi>Clement Joynes,</hi> of this Pariſh, upon mature Deliberation, and full Conviction of the many and great <hi>Errours</hi> which I have faln into, and zealouſly maintaind', for near <hi>Seven Years</hi> paſt, Declare and Acknowledge to this Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation my hearty Repentance for the ſame, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deſiring to be Admitted again into the Communion of the Church of <hi>England</hi> eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd by Law, into which I was Baptiz'd, and from which I have Raſhly and Ignorantly departed.</p>
            <p>I confeſs with Shame and Confuſion, that in the Year 1694 I was deluded by the <hi>Quakers,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:59049:3"/>and embrac'd, with great fervency, their <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Hereſies</hi> and <hi>Monſtrous Principles,</hi> till of late Examining 'em more carefully, by the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of God's Grace, I diſcover'd their Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and Impiety, and how directly contrary they were to the Holy Scriptures, particularly in their Denying the LORD that Bought them; by Diſowning <hi>that</hi> Jeſus, who ſuffer'd on the Croſs, to be the Son of God: Alſo for their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying that his Human Body aſcended into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and throwing aſide, with ſcorn and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, the <hi>Holy Sacraments</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> together with the <hi>Belief of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Dead.</hi> Theſe, with many Other <hi>Groſs Errours,</hi> which may be ſeen more at large in a late Book call'd, <hi>The Quaker's Creed,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining 13 Articles, I acknowledge I did Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and Defend: But do now utterly Deteſt, Abhor and Renounce, with all others, inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with the Doctrin of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> whoſe 39 <hi>Articles</hi> I have carefully conſider'd, and do hereby Declare that I do own, as the <hi>Summe</hi> and <hi>Subſtance</hi> of my <hi>Faith;</hi> deſiring to continue in the <hi>Communion of that Church</hi> while I Live, and to Dye the Death of the faithful Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59049:3"/>
            <p>And whereas I did not only fall thus dread fully my ſelf, but labour'd, with great dilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, to miſlead ſeveral of my neareſt Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Friends, and did unhappily ſucceed in doing ſo; I acknowledge, with unfeigned ſorrow, this ſad aggravation of my Crime, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing ſolemnly in the Preſence of God, (of which I deſire you All to be Witneſſes) that I will faithfully endeavour to Reclaim every one of them; and I bleſs my gracious God, from the bottom of my heart, that I have already Recover'd ſome, who are now here preſent.</p>
            <p>During my Doubts concerning the <hi>Quakers Doctrine,</hi> I went to <hi>George Whitehead,</hi> the Chief of them, and Ask'd him with Reſpect and Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to inform me upon what my Salvation did depend: After ſome little Diſcourſe, but no Offence given, or intended by me, he ſpoke theſe Words with ſome Paſſion: <hi>Repent ſpeedily, or elſe the Lord will confound thee; Thou readeſt Enemies Books — Young Man, I caution thee, not to take pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice againſt any Friend; for, if thou doſt, the Lord will Confound thee, and bring thee to nought. And this is the Word of the Lord to thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59049:4"/>
            <p>But tho' I was thus Us'd, and tho' I do hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily Abhor and Deteſt the aforeſaid Errours, yet I bleſs God that I have Charity for all thoſe of my former Acquaintance among the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and earneſtly beg of You to join with me in my Prayers, that it may pleaſe God to bring them into the Way of Truth, and give them a right Knowledge of the only Redeemer Chriſt Jeſus, God and Man: <hi>To Whom, with the Father, and Holy Spirit, be all Honour and Glory, both now and for evermore,</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59049:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd at St. <hi>Clements Danes.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Pſal. <hi>66.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Come and Hear all ye that Fear God, and I will declare what he hath done for my Soul.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THESE Words were the Choice of the Perſon whoſe Recantation you have heard, in order to the ſetting forth farther the Sincerity of his Repentance, and the greatneſs of the danger from which he has been deliver'd, that others may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd to avoid the ſame, and join with him in the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God accordingly. Which deſign has ſo much of Juſtice and Goodneſs in it, that as I am order'd to Comply with it by Authority, ſo I willingly and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Obey.</p>
            <p>And indeed the Words are very proper for this Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; for, not to inſiſt upon the particular Occaſion, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the Pſalmiſt might ſpeak them, they afford us a moſt excellent Example, How any Perſon, who has fall'n into great Errours, either as to Faith or Practice, and afterwards upon his ſincere Repentance, felt the Joys of Forgiveneſs, and the bleſſed Tranſports of being reſtor'd to a good Conſcience, ought to behave himſelf
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59049:5"/>both to his Neighbour, and to his God. This will appear, if we conſider them more particularly in this manner.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Perſons whom the Pſalmiſt appeals to, <hi>All ye that fear God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Publick Acknowledgments which he makes of God's mercy to him (including alſo his own Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs,) and his Earneſtneſs with them, to give him Attention, <hi>Come, and hear, and I will declare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Greatneſs of the Benefit which he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, under thoſe Words, <hi>What he hath done for my Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Come, and hear, all Ye that fear God, and I will declare what he hath done for my Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt thing which deſerves our conſideration is, the Perſons to whom the Pſalmiſt appeals, <hi>All ye that fear God;</hi> that is, All of what Rank or Degree what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, that had a due Senſe of Religion and Virtue, that had a well-grounded, and well-govern'd Zeal for God's Glory: Theſe were the Perſons that were moſt likely to afford him Attention, to be pleas'd with his being Reconcil'd to God, and to join with him in his Praiſe and Thankſgiving. As for thoſe who do not fear God, but are looſe in their Belief, and conſequently looſe in their Practice, they wou'd have been ſo far from being pleas'd with any thing of this kind (even in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> himſelf) that they wou'd rather have condemn'd, or deſpis'd it. For as ſuch People know little what a good Conſcience is, ſo they cannot be much Concern'd at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others being reſtor'd to it; and as they do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in God at all, ſo what is it to them who is in the Right, or the Wrong? who perſiſts in his Errours, or who forſakes them? Nay, the latter is the more Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive, the more publickly 'tis done: Becauſe when a Man acknowledges <hi>His</hi> Errours with Sorrow and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, he ſeems to upbraid them for continuing obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59049:5"/>
               <hi>in theirs:</hi> If it be an <hi>Abomination to Fools</hi> (as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> call thoſe who are Impudent and Stubborn in their Wickedneſs) <hi>to depart from Evil</hi> themſelves, 13 <hi>Prov.</hi> 19. Is it poſſible they ſhou'd be ſatisfy'd when others do ſo? Or if ſuch Wretches <hi>make a Mock of Sin,</hi> will they not make a <hi>Mock of Repentance</hi> alſo? Therefore the Pſalmiſt does not Appeal here to the mixt multitude of <hi>Jews,</hi> much leſs to all Mankind, but to thoſe alone, who fear'd God. And theſe undoubtedly were tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with holy Joy at what he related to them. How much more will they be ſo in the like Caſes, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve truly in the Son of God: For they who are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways remembring the ſweet Commands of Mercy and Love, which the Goſpel of Peace breaths out continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally; they who have always before their Eyes thoſe Holy Examples of Goodneſs and Charity, which our bleſſed Lord left us; will alſo have a tender Concern upon them for the Good of their Neighbour, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in what relates to the Salvation of his Soul, and therefore will rejoice to ſee him Recover'd from the very brink of Ruin, to behold him turning back, when juſt falling into Eternal Damnation; 'tis to theſe then alone that we Appeal at preſent in the Words of the Text, <hi>Come, and hear, all ye that fear God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us conſider the Publickneſs of that Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment which he deſign'd to make, and his Earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with them, to Attend to him, <hi>Come, and hear, and I will declare unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho' <hi>David</hi> was a very great Prince, and the Sins which he fell into were very great, both in their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and their Circumſtances; as being againſt much Knowledge, and long Experience of God's Goodneſs, and therefore the more Shameful; yet He is always ready to make a Publick Confeſſion of them; as He
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59049:6"/>does particularly in the 51 <hi>Pſal.</hi> upon the Matter of <hi>Uriah.</hi> But Humane Nature generally is very Averſe to this, whither in Returning from Error to Truth, or from Vice to Virtue: With what ſtrange Confidence do ſome Men Value themſelves upon the fouleſt Vices! With what Impudence do others Scoff at all Religion, and Blaſpheme the Son of God! With what Harden'd Obſtinacy and ſullen Bitterneſs do others again Break thro' all the Laws of Modeſty and Charity, to bear their Teſtimony to the Groſſeſt Errors! but if thro' the Mercy of God, they become ſenſible of this, and cool by Degrees from the Violent Heats of Debauchery or Enthuſiaſm, and are Willing to Return again to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to their God; yet how full of Fear and Shame are they? With what Caution and Privacy do they Proceed? What care is taken to ſecure their Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our or cover their Reputation, leſt they ſhould be Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd for want of Judgment, or Levity, and Inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: But how Unreaſonable is this! The want of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſurely was Diſcovered at firſt, in the falling into Error, nor in the Diſclaiming it; ſo the Levity and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy was Notorious, in the Turning out of the Right way, into every Dirty By-Lane; and miſtaking the Hot Vapours of a Diſtemper'd Brain for the Light of Revelation: To perſiſt in an Error, for fear of being Cenſur'd by Weak and Wicked Men, for leaving it, is Obſtinacy not Conſtancy; 'tis the Walking on ſteddily to Hell, in Compliance to our Acquaintance; for 'tis not only making Reaſon Uſeleſs, but doing deſpight to the Spirit of Grace, denying the Holy Jeſus, while we pretend to profeſs Him, and putting Him to Open Shame, to ſecure ones own Reputation.</p>
            <p>Whereas if Men conſidered things impartially, if they reflected as they ought to do upon the Majeſty of that God, whom they have offended, how much his Honour and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59049:6"/>Glory ſuffers by any Wickedneſs, but eſpecially by foul Apoſtacy, and Enormous Crimes; how the Saving Name of <hi>Jeſus</hi> is expos'd to the Blaſphemy of Atheiſts and Infidels; while People Embrace ſuch Doctrines as make Void his Croſs, and Render the Blood of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant ſhed there, a common or Contemptible thing: If, I ſay, they wou'd be ſenſible of this, then ſure, the leaſt that they can do wou'd be to acknowledge pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly that they are ſo. In Quarrels which happen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween one another, before Company, To ask Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in Private, is not look'd upon as ſufficient Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction; but this muſt be as Publick at leaſt as the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury was; Alas! ſhall we proceed ſo nicely in the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle miſtakes between Brethren and Fellow Chriſtians, and yet Scruple to do any thing of this Nature, after we have been Guilty of the Greateſt Sins, of Deſerting, or Rebelling againſt, the moſt High and moſt Holy God: The uſe of this is twofold.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That ſince Men are ſo generally averſe, ſo very much aſham'd to own their Errours, and this ſtill the more, the greater thoſe Errours are: Where People Break thro' theſe Difficulties to own in the Face of the World, Errors of the Groſſeſt kind; we ought to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied of their Sincerity and Conclude with ourſelves, that they do that upon mature Deliberation, and firm Reſolution, which they chuſe to do before ſo many Witneſſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That what is ſo done, and muſt be ſo acceptable to God, ought to Raiſe our Value and eſteem for ſuch Perſons, and Reſtore them (as well in Juſtice to themſelves as for the Encouragement of others) not only to our good. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, but our Friendſhip and Affection; for who is there that does really fear God himſelf, that wou'd not Run forth in Holy Joy, to meet any miſtaken Chriſtian, Retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to His Duty? that wou'd not Embrace him with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59049:7"/>the moſt tonder Compaſſion and Love, and Praiſe and Magnify with him, the Father of Mercies, <hi>forasmuch as this their</hi> Brother <hi>was Dead, but is alive again, was loſt, but is ſound?</hi> This I am perſuaded Every one wou'd Gladly do, when they conſider Attentively the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Benefit Receiv'd, which is our</p>
            <p n="3">3d. Point. The moſt Important indeed of all, inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in theſe Words, <hi>what He hath done for my Soul.</hi> As this concerns the Pſalmiſt, the Benefit for which He Praiſes God, was, as may be ſeen by the Verſes follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>God's Accepting of his Humiliation and Prayers, and Reſtoring him to the Peace of a Good Conſcience.</hi> But to bring this directly to the Caſe in Hand, Namely the Greatneſs of the Mercy which this Perſon hath Receiv'd, together with theſe others his Friends and Acquaintance here Preſent, and to move you to join with them in Praiſing of God accordingly, it will be neceſſary to ſhew you the Greatneſs of that Danger which they have been in, and the monſtrous Errours, which the People call'd <hi>Quakers,</hi> with whom they lately joined, are fallen into, concerning the Fundamental Articles of our Faith.</p>
            <p>This will be done moſt fairly and Impartially, by Quoting to you their own Words in ſeveral Remarkable Paſſages, taken out of ſuch Books, as were Written by their firſt or chief Teachers, and are ſtill own'd by them, ſuch, I ſay, as I have perus'd and Examin'd Diligently my ſelf, and moſt of them, <hi>with others,</hi> upon a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular occaſion.</p>
            <p>Whereas then it is moſt plainly and poſitively af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd in the holy Scriptures: <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt, the Son of God, was Conceiv'd of the Holy Ghoſt, made Fleſh, and Born of the Virgin</hi> Mary: <hi>That he was put to Death upon the Croſs: That thro' his Blood-ſhed there we have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption: That as he Died for our Sins, ſo he Roſe again for our Juſtification, in the ſame Body in which he was Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cify'd;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59049:7"/>which very Temple of his Body (ſo call'd, becauſe the Fulneſs of the God-head dwealt in it Bodily.) He fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told he would Raiſe again: That this Chriſt is our Peace with God— having Aboliſhed in <hi>His Fleſh,</hi> the Enmity</hi> (between God and Men,) (Eph. 2. v. 14.15.) <hi>that it pleas'd the Father, Chriſt having made Peace <hi>thro' the Blood of his Croſs,</hi> by him to reconcile all things to himſelf— <hi>In the Body of His Fleſh thro Death</hi>
               </hi> Coloſſ. 1.19, 20.22. <hi>That he aſcended up into Heaven in the ſame Body, and ſat down at the Right hand of God,</hi> to the end, <hi>That we might enter thither into the Holieſt by the Blood of Jeſus, by a new and living way which he hath Conſecrated for Us, thro' the Veil, that is to ſay <hi>His Fleſh,</hi>
               </hi> Heb. 10.19, 20. <hi>That the ſame Jeſus, who did Aſcend in the ſight of many of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, ſhall ſo come in like manner in the ſame Body, viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in the Clouds of Heaven, to Judge both the Quick and the Dead.</hi> Whereas, I ſay, theſe Articles of our Faith are thus plainly deliver'd in theſe, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Texts of Scripture, and generally Agreed to by, I think, moſt Diſſenters. Theſe unhappy People, the <hi>Quakers,</hi> either utterly deny 'em, or make 'em void, by applying them to their Light within, which they call Chriſt. Rejecting the Merits of our bleſſed Lord's Blood <hi>Outwardly Shed,</hi> and the Sacrifice of his Body upon the Croſs at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us prove this Charge in its ſeveral Particulars.</p>
            <p>And in order to this, let me deſire you to take par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Notice of this Great and Fundamental Errour upon which they raiſe all the reſt, <hi>viz. Their Diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing between two Chriſts;</hi> the Chriſt who Suffer'd at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> whom they call the <hi>Outward Chriſt;</hi> and their Light, which they call the <hi>Chriſt within;</hi> which is the only Chriſt they value, or depend upon.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then as to the Incarnation: This they reckon no otherwiſe beneficial, than as Chriſt is Incarnate in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59049:8"/>
               <hi>Quaker.</hi> That the true Chriſt is he that is Born within them, who grows up by degrees from an Holy Seed to a Child, and then to be the mighty God; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying commonly in their Writings upon this occaſion that Celebrated Propheſy of <hi>Iſaiah, Chap.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 6, unto each particular <hi>Quaker,</hi> Man or Woman, <hi>Unto Us a Child is born, unto Us a Son is given, and the Government ſhall be upon his Shoulders, and his Name ſhall be call'd Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful, Counſellor, the Mighty God, the Everlaſting Father, the Prince of Peace.</hi> Thus one of them: <hi>Be thou the Virgin, and the Power of the Moſt High ſhall over-ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow thee; and that holy Thing which ſhall be Born of thee, ſhall be called the Son of God. William Baily's</hi> Works, <hi>p.</hi> 292, 293. <hi>Faith in Chriſts <hi>Outward Manifeſtation,</hi> has been a Deadly Poiſon this latter Age has been infected with all, (Quakeriſm, a New Nick Name,</hi> p. 6.)</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſame they affirm concerning the Sufferings of Chriſt; theſe are to be perform'd within them too, or elſe are to no Purpoſe, and the Blood of the Seed ſhed within them, (as they ſpeak) is ſufficient of it ſelf to juſtify them in the Sight of God, and reject with Scorn and Diſdain, <hi>that which was ſhed by our Saviour Outwardly. Thus Mr.</hi> Penn, <hi>we deny juſtification, by the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, fullfill'd <hi>in his own Perſon,</hi> for us (wholly without us) and boldly affirm it in the Name of the Lord, to be the Doctrine of Devils,</hi> O Horrid Blaſphemy! <hi>and an Arm of that Sea of Corruption, which does now deluge the whole World.</hi> Mr. <hi>Penn</hi>'s Serious Apology. p. 148.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>That the Outward Perſon, which ſuffer'd, was properly the Son of God, we utterly deny.</hi> Ib. 146.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If there be any other Chriſt, but he that was Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd within, <hi>He is a falſe Chriſt,</hi> and the Devil never made it, (i: e.)</hi> this Doctrine, as was Objected to him) <hi>but he and his Meſſengers, are againſt it. The Devils</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:59049:8"/>and Reprobates may talk of him without. <hi>G. Fox Gr. Myſt.</hi> p. 206.</p>
            <p>Nay, they affirm farther, that a Quaker may arrive to ſuch perfection, that, He may forget wholly, the Chriſt which dy'd at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Thus Another of them: <hi>When you come to know this,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> the Operation of Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in) <hi>you will ceaſe Remembring his Death at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and will come to ſee How He has been Crucified in you.</hi> p. 19. Doctr. of Perfection Vindic. by <hi>J. Whitehouſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. As for the Reſurrection, This Mr <hi>Penn</hi> compares upon account of the Abſurdity of it, to Tranſubſtantiation: <hi>Reaſon ag. Railing, p.</hi> 134. and thoſe Remarkable Paſſages concerning the Reſurrection of the Body, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 15. they apply to the Reſurrection of the Soul by Faith, alone, from a Natural to a Spiritual Eſtate. Which is the very Same Error with that of <hi>Hymnaeus</hi> and <hi>Phile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> which St <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. c. 17, 18. <hi>Who concerning the faith have erred, ſaying the Reſurrection is paſs'd</hi> already, <hi>and overthrow the Faith of ſome:</hi> St <hi>Paul</hi> Himſelf was in the ſame ſtate of Reſurrection (as I hope they will allow) which they ſpeak of; and yet He Condemn'd thoſe who taught this as the only Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, as overthrowers of the Faith.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As to Chriſts aſcenſion and ſitting at the Right Hand of God. This they Affirm to be done <hi>within 'em only, as neceſſary to Salvation:</hi> the teaching the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they call ſetting ones ſelf Againſt Chriſt. Thus when one <hi>J. Wrightſon</hi> had dedicated a Book He wrote Againſt them; <hi>To all them that Call upon the Name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſits at the Right Hand of God the Father in the Heavens, out of Every Man on Earth;</hi> in a Preface to a Book call'd <hi>the Son of Perdition Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd, by the light of the Son of God in his Servants</hi> Geo. Whitehead <hi>and</hi> Ed. Burroughs; they deſire it may be noted, How <hi>J. W.</hi> had abſolutely <hi>ſet Himſelf againſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59049:9"/>Chriſt and the Truth, who herein hath Gone about to limit and divide the Holy one from his People and members</hi>— Which they Explain farther afterwards—<hi>In that</hi> J. W. <hi>hath accounted Chriſt as He is at the Right Hand of God the Father not to be in Any man, but out of Every Man upon Earth:</hi> He hath gone about to Separate the Saints from the Right Hand of God; <hi>and ſo hath diſcover'd Himſelf Both Ignorant of Chriſt, and of the Fathers Right Hand, and of the Kingdom of Heaven in the Saints, for they that are come to Chriſt, and to Know Him in them; they Are come to the Fathers Right Hand; and being Chriſts Sheep, none ſhall pull them out of His Fathers Hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in a Primmer which they teach their Poor In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Children (by <hi>William Smith</hi>) diſtinguiſhing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the True and the Falſe Preachers, <hi>They that are falſe</hi> (ſays this Author) <hi>Preach Chriſt without, and bid people Believe in Him as He is in Heaven above.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this one alone would have been ſufficient to Raiſe in You Horrour and Amazement. <hi>Your Imagin'd God beyond the Stars, and Your Carnal Chriſt is utterly deny'd — To ſay this Chriſt is God and man in one Perſon, is a Lye. C. Atkinſon</hi>'s Sword of the Lord drawn, p. 5.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Concerning Chriſts coming to Judgment, take this one alone from <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> above-mention'd, now living. <hi>Doſt Thou Look for Chriſt as the Son of</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>to appear outwardly in a Bodily Exiſtence, to ſave Thee, according to thy works? If Thou doſt, Thou mayſt look till thy Eyes drop out, before Thou wilt ſee ſuch an Appearance of Him.</hi> Nature of Chriſtianity, p. 29, 30.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſome of their Horrid Blaſphemies, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Fundamentals of our Holy Religion, and the Chief Articles of our Creed, which notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all this, They Pretend to Own; and to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, have publiſh'd, (as they have been taxt with theſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59049:9"/>Impieties,) ſome Accounts of their Faith, Deluding the Ignorant, and Covering themſelves, by Applying <hi>to their Chriſt within,</hi> which is their Conſtant way of Equivocation, whatever <hi>We ſay of our Chriſt without.</hi> Meaning, I ſay, always that what they affirm concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt, is perform'd as to His Birth, Sufferings, Reſurrection, and Aſcenſion, as theſe are neceſſary to Salvation, within every true Quaker.</p>
            <p>The Holy Scriptures teach us, that the True Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of that Faith which Juſtifies, is Chriſt Jeſus mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in the Fleſh, Both God and Man; That it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that a Spotleſs Sacrifice ſhould be offered to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe the Juſtice of the Father; that it being impoſſible any man ſhould be ſo perfectly innocent as to make A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement for others; or that God ſhould ſuffer as God; He took the Nature of Man upon Him as to its Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in all Reſpects, Excepting Sin alone; that He Suffer'd and Dy'd, Roſe again, and aſcended in the ſame Nature, and that we obtain Forgiveneſs by the Merits of his ſo doing, without any Merits of our own, But by Applying, by the Aſſiſtance of the Holy Spirit, and a Lively Faith, what <hi>He did Thus out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, inwardly to our Souls.</hi> For They teach further, that as a Proof of the Sincerity of this Faith, and as a means of Holineſs of Life, We ſhould by the Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Operations of the Holy Spirit, which God has Promis'd to the Faithful, imitate Chriſt in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Parts of what He did for our Redemption, by Dying Unto Sin, by Riſing again to a Life of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; by aſcending alſo after our Saviour, by Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our Affections on things above, on himſelf eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, the Great and Glorious Object of our Love, Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Adoration.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:59049:10"/>
            <p>Now what is thus done, is not performed by Chriſts being Perſonally in any one of Us, but by the Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the Holy Spirit moving and concurring with us; nor would it be of any Benefit to us, were it not for that which Chriſt did and ſuffered for Us: All theſe operations <hi>in</hi> and <hi>of</hi> the Soul, would according to the Covenant of Grace contained in the Goſpel, ſignify nothing at all for the attaining Eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but only as they depend upon the Merits of that Blood, that <hi>Humane and Material Blood ſhed</hi> by Chriſt at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Quakers are for the Inward only: What is done in the Soul, they Reckon to be done by Chriſt Himſelf; embody'd, as it were, and Perſonally in them, upon which Ground, <hi>G. Fox</hi> accepted, and defended with Blaſphemous Pride the Adoration which was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Him. They teach, that Chriſt is actually Born, and ſuffers in every one of them, in order to His being a compleat Quaker. Thus they make Void the Croſs of our Gracious Redeemer, and deſtroy all the Subſtance of Chriſtianity, which Evaporates by this means into a Vain Allegory. And the Conſequence of this is, that they Utterly Reject <hi>Chriſts outward Ordinances,</hi> His Bleſſed Sacraments, and deſpiſe the Holy Scriptures, unleſs when they think 'em of their Side, till their Wild Enthuſiaſm ends in a Blaſphemous Pretence to Sinleſs Perfection, Infallibility and Equality with God.</p>
            <p>Their Errors in theſe particulars, 'twill be neceſſary to lay before you alſo, and that I ſhall do in the ſame manner as before, by producing their own Words.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the Holy Sacraments or Outward Baptiſm. This they call <hi>Idolatry;</hi> a Carnal Empty Shadow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as in the Treat, above-mentioned (Son of Perdition Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd by <hi>G. Whitehead,</hi> and <hi>E. Burroughs,</hi> p. 26.)</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:59049:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>All may ſee</hi> what Idolatry <hi>He,</hi> (<hi>J. W.</hi> their Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent) <hi>is in about</hi> Water, and <hi>How he is Muddled in His Confuſion, tho He without juſt Cauſe is offended that</hi> we count their Baptiſm a Carnal Empty Shadow, or low thing that God is gone out of, <hi>tho it be</hi> both True and Apparent enough, <hi>ſince they make ſuch an</hi> Idol of it; <hi>and Practice it either</hi> without <hi>immediate Command from Heaven, or motion of Gods ſpirit for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame <hi>Burroughs</hi> again (Collect. of his Works, p. 190.) <hi>To ſay that ſprinkling Infants with Water is Baptiſm into the Faith of Chriſt, is the</hi> Doctrine of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils.</p>
            <p>And <hi>G. Fox,</hi> their Founder: <hi>Your Baptiſm and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, as ye call them, and all your Ordinances,</hi> and <hi>Churches,</hi> and <hi>Teaching,</hi> is <hi>Cain</hi>'s Sacrifice—<hi>Their Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as they call it, is Carnal, their Communion Bread and Wine, is the Table of Devils, and the Doctrine of Devils,</hi> p. 14. News out of the North, Written from the mouth of the Lord, from one who is naked, and who ſtandeth naked before the Lord, cloathed with Righteouſneſs, whoſe Name is not known in the World, riſen up out of the North, which was prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy'd of, but now is fulfilled, called <hi>George Fox.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Concerning the Scriptures: <hi>Duſt is the Serpents meat: their Original is but Duſt, which is but the Letter,</hi> which is <hi>Death. So theſe Serpents feed upon Duſt, which feed upon all thoſe carnal things, and their Goſpel is Duſt,</hi> Matthew, Mark, Luke <hi>and</hi> John; <hi>which is the Letter:</hi> (News out of the North, p. 14.) the Curſed Serpent is in the Letter; Truths defence, by <hi>R. Hubberthorn,</hi> p. 102. This alone is too much upon this Head.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Concerning Sinleſs Perfection; <hi>A tittle of the Law is ſeen not to be broken</hi>— this (ſaith <hi>G. Fex</hi>) is Known in Us: <hi>Great Myſtery,</hi> p. 310.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:59049:11"/>
            <p>Upon that of St <hi>James:</hi> In many things we Offend all, mark, in the many things we offend all, <hi>but we are come to the one thing, Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, the End of the many things; and in Him there is no ſin, and who is in Him ſins not, who put an End to the many things that muſt End and Change. (Great Myſtery,</hi> p. 309.) An Admirable Comment.</p>
            <p>And in the Abundance of this Vanity Mr <hi>Penn</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to us, (<hi>Truth Exalted,</hi> p. 9. Reprinted 1671.) the Praying <hi>from Seven to Seventy, Have Mercy upon us miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Sinners,</hi> Which Mr <hi>Whitehead</hi> ſeconds with Great Charity and Humility. <hi>Alas poor Sinners! It's not a ſign of Laughter at them, but rather of Lamentation and Pity over their miſerable Eſtate, who are always confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, but not forſaking their Sins,</hi> (Truth and Innocence, p. 15.) and upon this ground <hi>George Fox</hi> Expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated with ſome of the Miniſtry, many years before. <hi>Are ye not worſe than the Lawyers and Phyſicians, taking the Peoples Money,</hi> and <hi>Yet cannot make them perfect men.</hi> Great Myſtery, p. 268.</p>
            <p>Again, as to Their Infallibility. <hi>Who witneſs theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, that</hi> they were in <hi>that gave forth the Scriptures, they witneſs Infallibility,</hi> an Infallible Spirit; Which is now Poſſeſſed and Witneſſed among thoſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Quakers? <hi>Glory to the Higheſt for ever!</hi> Oh Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid!— And a little after, <hi>I ſay the Devil, Falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Antichriſts, Deceivers,</hi> (which are the Names they give to all that differ from them, or write againſt them) <hi>none of theſe can witneſs an Infallible Spirit— But being out of the Spirit, that Chriſt, the Prophets and the Apoſtles was in, they are not Infallible as they were; but with that they are all Judged out.</hi> Gr. Myſt. p. 105.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:59049:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>But of themſemſelves they ſay again, <hi>Our Giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth Books and Printed Papers,</hi> it is <hi>from the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Eternal Spirit of God,</hi> to the <hi>ſhewing forth the Filthy Practices of the World's teachers,</hi> Truths Def. p. 2.</p>
            <p>And <hi>George Fox</hi> ſpeaking of other Preachers, <hi>ſays they are Conjurers and Diviners, and their teaching is from Conjuration, which is ſpoke from the mouth of the Lord; and the Lord is againſt all ſuch, and Who are of God are againſt all ſuch: (Sauls</hi> Errand to <hi>Damaſ.</hi> p. 7.)</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>Concerning Equality with God. They that have the Spirit of God,</hi> (meaning themſelves) <hi>are equal with God. He that is joyned to the Lord, is one ſpirit, there is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity: and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity ſtand in Equality it ſelf.</hi> F. Howgills <hi>Work, p.</hi> 232.</p>
            <p>He that hath the ſame Spirit <hi>that raiſed up Jeſus Chriſt is equal with God, and the Saints have the ſame ſpirit in meaſure, for Gods Spirit is but one, (Saul</hi>'s Errand by <hi>G. F.</hi> p. 8.)</p>
            <p>Which he confirms in another place, <hi>the Aſſemblies Catechiſm ſays, The Holy Ghoſt and Son was equal in Subſtance und Power and Glory with the Father.</hi> What? (ſays he) <hi>then all that have the Son and the Holy Ghoſt, hath that which is Equal in Power and Glory with the Father.</hi> G. Myſt. p. 248.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſome of the Errors which this Unhappy and Deluded People are led into; I mention not their Blaſphemies againſt the Holy Trinity, and their Scorn and Contempt of the Civil Power, but for a further account of theſe and other Errors, recommend to your Peruſal that Excellent Book called <hi>The Snake in the Graſs,</hi> with other Writings of the ſame Author upon this Subject. Alſo what the Learned Mr <hi>Keith</hi> has pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed ſince His Retractations.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:59049:12"/>
            <p>And now Brethren, Who is there in all this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany whoſe Blood has not been chill'd with a Sudden damp of Horrour at the very Recital of ſo many dreadful Blaſphemies! and who is there that has ſo little fear of God, or Love for his Neighbour, as not to magnifie and adore His Great mercy to theſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whom He has at length Truly enlighten'd, by His Bleſſed Spirit; Recover'd from Such Errors, as without Repentance might have ended in Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and <hi>done ſo much, ſo very much for their Souls.</hi> And oh! that we might Ever ſee that Happy day! When the reſt of our Country-men, (I am ſorry I cannot ſay our fellow Chriſtians) <hi>ſhall Return to Sion, and build up the Walls of Jeruſalem,</hi> which they have made Such Breaches in; Acknowledge their dreadful Errors, and Give God the Glory. But this is a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing very little to be Expected, becauſe very little De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd: Alas! it muſt be confeſt, that the Sins of this Nation are too great, for it to be delivered from ſo Heavy a Judgment; and yet the very heavineſs of it ought to move us to Repentance; for this is greater in itſelf, if rightly conſidered, than Fire, War or Plague can be, for thoſe deſtroy only our Eſtates or Lives; and while they are doing ſo, often make us Better; But Deluſion of this kind ſpreads with a ſilent yet deadly Infection, to the utter deſtruction of many thouſand Souls.</p>
            <p>And withal, this particular Evil is ſo deeply Root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and of ſo Stubborn a Kind, as being Compos'd of all the Hereſies of Old, and fixt and ſettled in thoſe it poſſeſſes by Enthuſiaſtick Retirements, by working themſelves into Bitter Agonies, which they call being under An Exerciſe, and by ſeparating themſelves by a Peculiar Language, Habit and Behaviour, all which Sowres at laſt into a Hatred and Contempt of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59049:12"/>Reſt of Mankind: this I ſay, is ſuch a Spirit of delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, upon all theſe accounts, as is not to be caſt out of this Nation, <hi>but by much Prayer and Faſting;</hi> By humbling our Selves greatly before the Father of Mercies for our Own Sins; and then interceeding with Him in all Tenderneſs and Charity for their Deluded Souls. And this is all the Force, theſe are all the Arms I deſire ſhould be Employ'd againſt them. What I have ſaid has not been with any deſign to Raiſe or Increaſe any Bitterneſs, or to Stir up Any Perſecution Againſt them, but to Shew the Goodneſs of God in Recovering theſe Perſons from Such a Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs Pit of Error and Darkneſs, and to Prevent others from falling into the ſame: And what I have quoted, Remains ſtill, in their Books not Retracted, but Rather Confirm'd by them; they Having So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly Reſolv'd to Stand by the Teſtimony of their Ancient Friends, (<hi>Yearly Ep.</hi> 1696.) meaning the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of their firſt Teachers, ſuch as I have recited, and yet at the Same Time they have bought up All the old Editions of ſuch Books, and have left out or alter'd ſeveral paſſages in their New ones, (<hi>See the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect at the end of the Defence of the Snake, Numb.</hi> 4.) and as to others, ſtrain'd and tortur'd the Words a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Ways, as ſome Parents ſerve their Crooked Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to Conceal, if Poſſible, their Odious Deformity. (<hi>This may be ſeen in the Anſwer to Mr</hi> Keith's <hi>firſt Narrative, and the</hi> Switch for the Snake; <hi>and prov'd Againſt 'em fully in</hi> Satan diſrob'd, the Defence of the Snake, <hi>and</hi> Mr <hi>Keith</hi>'s Fourth Narrative)</p>
            <p>Such is the miſery and folly of the Pretence of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility, where-ever it obtains. In the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> many were for giving up ſome of the Doctrines, which they were ſenſible were directly Againſt the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures; and this was in a likely way of Succeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59049:13"/>till the Popes Creatures began to Repreſent, How much the Dignity and Authority of the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> muſt be hazarded, and How they muſt forfeit for Ever their Darling Principle of Infallibility; and then all was daſh'd in a moment: So, much more are ſome men concern'd to Secure their Intereſt than to Confeſs their Errors; and to Gratifie their Pride, than to Obey their Conſciences. And indeed, Conſidering the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors which theſe poor People Hold; their infallibility, which we have been Speaking of, their Contempt of the Scripture, with the Boaſts of their own Perfection; which are the fundamental Errors of the Papiſts; and alſo the Hindring of the Common People of their Perſwaſion, <hi>from Reading the Books of Truths Enemies,</hi> as they call all that write and ſpeak againſt them; the Equivocations and Reſerves in their way of writing, to which they Retire like retrenchments, as oft as they are driven from one to another; and the Odd Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of the worſt of the Primitive Hereſies, which are Recorded in <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Languages, unknown to their firſt Teachers; I do not doubt, but that the Miſſionaries of <hi>Rome</hi> have been very buſie in ſowing their tares among them while the Nation ſlept, and never regarded a Sect, which they thought ought to be Pity'd for their Innocence, or Deſpis'd for their Ignorance. Upon this Account it is that the inferiour ſort eſpecially Really deſerve our Kindneſs and Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. But moſt of all upon the Account of that Holy Religion which we Profeſs. That Jeſus! who came in the Fleſh, <hi>that outward Chriſt which they deny,</hi> and deprive themſelves, by ſo doing, of the moſt perfect Pattern of Charity and Mercy; that Jeſus, I ſay, <hi>Who Requires us to Love our Enemies, to Bleſs them that Curſe us,</hi> and <hi>Pray for them that Deſpightfully uſe us.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, Never had we ſo much occaſion to Practiſe this Command as they have given us.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:59049:13"/>
            <p>But Charity is to extend to our Paſſions, and not our Underſtandings; and therefore the ſame Jeſus, who Commands this Commands us alſo to beware of falſe Prophets, who cry, Lo here is Chriſt! or there is Chriſt! Whither in a Wafer, by Tranſubſtantion, or in a ſinful Body, by the light within; theſe muſt be falſe Chriſts; becauſe, (among other Reaſons,) they are many Chriſts, whereas there is and can be but one, but He alone, Who is now interceeding for us at the Right Hand of God, and Who gave us this particular Caution to direct us, and prevent vain Excuſes, <hi>See I have told you before.</hi> In order then to our Obeying it, let me give you three ſhort Rules, and then I ſhall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That We ſhould carefully beware of this Spirit of Enthuſiaſm which is gone out in this Age, that we ſhould be cautious How we Humour any Religious Melancholy, to ſuch a degree, as to Expect continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally new Revelations, and when the Soul is ſuſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Scruples, Terrours and Amazement, take every Sudden thought which Flaſhes in the Heated Fancy, to be immediate Inſpiration. The Apoſtle St <hi>John,</hi> our Lord's Beloved Diſciple, cautions us with all the meekneſs of the Spirit of Peace. Beloved, believe not every Spirit, but try the Spirits whether they are of God, becauſe many falſe Prophets are gone out into the World, 1ſt Epiſt. <hi>John</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. One Rule He gives in the next Verſe, which would be ſufficient to detect thoſe we have to do withal, if <hi>Rightly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd,</hi> viz. <hi>Hereby Know Ye the Spirit of God, Every Spirit that confeſſeth that Jeſus</hi> is come in the Fleſh <hi>is of God,</hi> and <hi>Every Spirit</hi> that Confeſſeth that Jeſus Chriſt is not come in the Fleſh <hi>is not of God; this is</hi> that <hi>Spirit of Antichriſt,</hi> which was come into the World e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in thoſe days, and which prevails in it too much
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59049:14"/>in ours: But there is a more General Rule whereby to Judge of any Spirit whatſoever, and that is the Word of God. Wherefore if any Pretended Prophet Riſes up with a New Light, and Contradicts directly all the Reſt, if two new Prophets riſe much about the ſame time, as <hi>Fox</hi> and <hi>Muggleton</hi> did, and oppoſe and Curſe one another, affirming both with like confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that they come from God; How ſhall any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon judge between them and the Reſt. There is no Rule given to this purpoſe but the Old and New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, and to theſe they ought to be brought for Examination, if what they teach be agreeable to what is Written there, 'tis no new light, but the better for being old, if it be not, 'tis in Vain to plead that it is inſpired by the Same Spirit, by which they were wrote, for that cannot Contradict itſelf, and therefore Whoever Contradicts that, muſt be Impos'd upon Himſelf, or have a deſign to impoſe Upon others. This Shews the Neceſſity of the Next Caution.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, That we ſhould take care How we neglect or undervalue thoſe Holy Writings our ſelves, or attend to thoſe who do ſo; Becauſe if this be once done, we have no Rule either of Faith or Practice left Us, and conſequently muſt Lye open to all Deluſion, and be blown about with every wind of Doctrine. The <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Romaniſts</hi> ſet up Tradition Equal to theſe, By which they provide an Excuſe not only for all the Errors Which they have fallen into already, but for All they ſhall think fitting to embrace Hereafter; for Who can fathom or diſcover the dark Abyſs of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; on the other ſide, all Enthuſiaſts ſet up Againſt them the Private Spirit, and all Atheiſts what they call Humane Reaſon, and ſo Wander in their different errors, or Wallow in their different Vices: for Private Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and Humane Reaſon amount to much the Same,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59049:14"/>and Signifie no More, but the Doing or Saying What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever each man Pleaſes. Wherefore we ſhould be very careful How we ſuffer any doubt to riſe in us concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Authority of thoſe Holy Writings, which Was ſo diligently inquir'd into, and ſo carefully ſettled in the firſt Ages of Chriſtianity: that we ſhould not throw away what is atteſted by ſo many miracles, and by the conſent of ſo many thouſands, and what is of ſo great importance to our Souls; upon account of any Cuſtom or Paſſage, which may ſeem ſtrange to Us; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider 'em as the Writings of Holy and Upright men, who were guided by the Infallible Spirit of God, and who Seal'd what they wrote by their own Blood. 'Tis therefore that theſe are Able to make us wiſe unto Salvation; and if theſe are able, what does there want elſe, or is it not ſufficient that they can make Us Wiſe unto Salvation? If any An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel from Heaven that Preach'd any other Doctrine than what is to be found there, ſhould be accurſed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to St <hi>Paul</hi>'s Sentence, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8. What ſhall we ſay of Any Quaker's Openings, (as they call their Pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Revelations;) which either ignorantly wreſt 'em, or inſolently Oppoſe them.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, That we ſhould take care How we indulge our Roving Fancies, in Leaving the Service of the Church, and Running up and down to Separate Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; which I mention the rather becauſe it was the Perſon's Caſe who is now particularly concern'd. This is dangerous, Becauſe no body can tell where it will End, For when the Soul has once been Us'd to Change, and our Faith becomes unſettled, it Either Runs into a Contempt of all Religion, or thinks none Good Enough for it, and ſo is becalmed in Atheiſm, or hurry'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Enthuſiaſm.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:59049:15"/>
            <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> was not Only the Glory of the Reformation, by the Purity of its Doctrine, and the Blood of its Martyrs, but has been the Support of it Ever Since, and Faithfully and Effectually oppos'd and defeated, from Time to Time, the Force, the Fraud and Learning of its moſt dangerous Enemies of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> This Sure may be ſaid at leaſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Envy. And yet upon what trifling Occaſions have many forſaken Her; ſome upon private quarrels or Perſonal Revenge; nay, ſome becauſe their Clothes have not been good Enough to be ſeen by their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, or becauſe they have not been Plac'd High Enough above them: Others through meer Levity and unſettledneſs of temper: together with a Great Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of themſelves; till having try'd all, they have left all too, and ſet up for diſtinct Churches, of themſelves. Thus Diviſions and Opinions have multiplied at laſt to ſuch a Degree, that we may too juſtly apply the words of the Prophet (<hi>Jerem.</hi> 2.18.) <hi>According to the Number of thy Cities</hi> (may I not ſay thy Towns, thy Villages) <hi>are thy Gods,</hi> O <hi>England!</hi> Behold then into how Wretched a Condition we Are fallen! What a Shame muſt this be to us, Who have ſo deſervedly upon other Accounts the Eyes of the World fixt Upon Us! and How muſt this Cauſe the Name of Jeſus to be Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phem'd by Infidels and Atheiſts! <hi>Hath a Nation Chang'd their Gods which are yet no Gods?</hi> Hath the Jews Quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their Law? or the Papiſts yielded up their Worſhip of Saints and Images? <hi>But my People have Chang'd their Glory for that which doth not Profit, (Jer.</hi> 2.11.) for Empty Noiſe, and Wild Geſtures; for Vain Pretences to Sinleſs Perfection, and Equality with God.</p>
            <p>But tho we ought to conſider theſe things with Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and Shame, Yet let us conſider them with Charity
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59049:15"/>too. Let this always be our diſtinguiſhing Character: By this let all men know who are the True Diſciples of the Holy Jeſus! And tho we ought to be Prepar'd al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways with Arguments, to give an Account of the Faith that is in us, yet all men are not Capable of Uſing theſe as they ſhould do; nor all men Capable of Receiving them. But there is one, that may be Us'd by the Young as well as the Old, the Poor as well as the Rich, and the Ignorant as the moſt Learned; One that inſinuates itſelf by degrees, Even through Raging Paſſion, Stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Pride, and Rooted Prejudice, and that is, <hi>a Good Life:</hi> Let this then be our Particular Care, and Let no Diſputes concerning the Groſſeſt Errors, Either Run us into a Hatred of the Perſons that maintain them, or into a Neglect of our own Duty.</p>
            <p>And, to Reflect once more Upon the Occaſion of this Diſcourſe, Let all thoſe Who Fear God, Who have any Tenderneſs for their Neighbour, or any Zeal for Gods Glory, Praiſe Him and Magnifie Him for Ever, for opening the Eyes and Hearts of theſe our Brethren, for delivering them from ſuch dreadful Errors, and ſhewing ſo great mercy, doing ſo very much for their Souls. But Thankſgiving is never ſo Acceptable as when Accompany'd by Charity. Therefore Let us Conclude all, by Joyning together in our Prayers to that God, who wouldeth not the Death of Any Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and Who is the God of Unity and Peace, that He would Heal up all our Breaches and Diviſions, that He would take from thoſe Who perſiſt in their Errors, All Ignorance, Hardneſs of Heart, and Contempt of his Word; that they and we may be made all together one fold, under one Shepherd, Jeſus Chriſt the Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>To whom,</hi> &amp;c,</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
